Guide to the Independent Union of Flight Attendants Records WAG.200
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Independent Union of Flight Attendants Records
1964-1991, (Bulk 1977-1988)
1977-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Independent Union of Flight Attendants
Hesse, Star D.
WAG.200
3 Linear Feet (3 boxes)
The Independent Union of Flight Attendants was formed in 1976 by flight attendants at Pan American Airlines who were dissatisfied with their working conditions and their representation by the Transport Workers Union of America. This collection includes correspondence, by-laws, minutes, contracts, newsletters, and printed material documenting the decertification of the TWU, formation of the IUFA, collective bargaining agreements with Pan American Airlines, and grievance cases from 1976 to 1991. It also contains files predating the formation of IUFA pertaining to flight attendants' concerns within TWU.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Star Hesse, 1992. The accession number associated with this gift is 1992.004.
The accession number NPA.2005.207 is also associated with this collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
In the mid-1970s, flight attendants at Pan American Airways (PAA) became dissatisfied with both their working conditions and their representation by the Transport Workers Union of America. In 1976, the flight attendants voted to decertify the TWU and form a new union, the Independent Union of Flight Attendants. Mary Ellen King served as the union's first president, and Alice Flynn as its vice president. Star Hesse, a flight attendant, got involved with IUFA in the late 1970s and became a section chairperson, negotiating contracts for the IUFA. In 1985, the flight attendants narrowly averted a walkout in support of striking TWU members. The IUFA dissolved when Pan American Airlines folded in 1991.
Issues of intense concern to the flight attendants, as reflected in their bargaining and grievance files and newsletters, were scheduling and seniority, overtime work, regulations on appearance and personal behavior and in-flight working conditions.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, by-laws, minutes, contracts, newsletters, and printed material documenting the decertification of the TWU, formation of the IUFA, collective bargaining agreements with Pan American Airways, and grievance cases from 1976 to 1991. In addition, it contains files predating the formation of IUFA pertaining to flight attendants' concerns within TWU.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 1 series:
Missing Title
I, General Files, 1964-1991
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Correspondence.; Women labor leaders |z United States.; Reports.; Collective bargaining |x Aeronautics |z United States.; Fliers (printed matter); Flight attendants |x Labor unions |z United States.; Flight attendants |z United States.; Hesse, Star D.; Pan American World Airways, Inc.; Transport Workers Union of America; Hesse, Star D.
- Series I: General Files, 1964-1991
  - Agreement - PAA/IUFA, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aircraft Literature, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Air Line Pilots Association: PAA Council Members, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appearance Standards, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Arbitration, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Arbitration: TWU/PAA, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Arbitration: Weight, 1982, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Arbitration: White House Press Charter, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Asbestos Complaint, 1981-1984 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Banked Hours, 1980-1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Bargaining, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bargaining, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bargaining, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bargaining, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Bargaining, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bargaining, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Bargaining, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bargaining, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Bargaining (and strike), 1978-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Cabin Attendant Reports (CAR's), 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Cases (Grievances, TWU), 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Charm School (In-Flight Services Training), 1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Constitutions, By-Laws and Policy Manual, 1978, 1981, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Continental: Bankruptcy (Bildisco) Case, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Contract Questionnaire, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Contract Survey, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Court Case: Anderson (Harassment), 1983 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Discrimination Cases: Lucinda Jameson, et al., 1980-1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Discrimination (EEOC Letters), 1981 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Dry Run Credit, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Duty Time Limit (TWU case), 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - FAA, 1980-1985 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - FACT Reports, 1986-1988 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Field Board of Adjustment: Briefs, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Field Board of Adjustment: Notes on hearing, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Firing: Ackerman Letter, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Firing: Pay Back, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Flex Flying, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Grebey, Ray, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Grievance: Francis Hamilton, 1974, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Grievance: Line Award, 1982-1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Grievance: OP Duty, 1978-1987 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Grievance: TACA, 1966-1972 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Grievance: Unresolved, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Health and Safety, 1970s (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Health and Safety, 1980s (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Health Benefits, 1976-1988 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Horst, James (TWU), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - H.O.T. Pay (Hours over thirteen), 1978-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Independent Federation of Flight Attendants/TWA Dispute, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Injunction against PAA, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Insubordination Case, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - IUFA: Annual Report, 1986-1987 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - IUFA: Correspondence, Undated, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - IUFA: Correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - IUFA: Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - IUFA: Elections, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - IUFA: Elections, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - IUFA: Elections, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - IUFA: Elections, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - IUFA: Finances, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - IUFA: Form Letters, 1978-1982 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - IUFA: Form Letters, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - IUFA: Minutes, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - IUFA: Newsletter (deletions), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - IUFA: Newsletters and Bulletins, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - IUFA: Newsletters and Bulletins, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - IUFA: Newsletters and Bulletins, 1982-1983 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - IUFA: Newsletters and Bulletins, 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - IUFA: Newsletters and Bulletins, 1987-1990 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - IUFA: Organizing, 1976-1983 (Box 2, Folder 24a)
  - IUFA: Petition, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 24b)
  - IUFA: Phone-In, undated (Box 2, Folder 24c)
  - IUFA: Staff/Board List, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - IUFA: Standards Committee, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Jumpseat Policy, 1980-1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Maternity Policy, 1984-1988 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - MCO Refund Denial, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Monthly Operational Bulletin, 1972-1977 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Monthly Operational Bulletin, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Monthly Operational Bulletin, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Monthly Operational Bulletin, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Monthly Operational Bulletin, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - National Transportation Safety Board, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - New York Base: Chairperson, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - New York Base: Newsletters and Memos, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - New Yorker Newsletter (In-Flight Services, JFK), 1978, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - New Yorker Newsletter (In-Flight Services, JFK), 1983-1986 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Nicolau Award, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Notes and Flyers, undated (Box 2, Folder 39a)
  - On Line Representation Program, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Pan American Airlines: Agreement, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Pan American Airlines: Bankruptcy, 1982-1991 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pan American Airlines: Contract Interpretation, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Pan American Airlines: Correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Pan American Airlines: Correspondence, 1981-1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Pan American Airlines: Early Retirement, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Pan American Airlines: Employee Ticketing, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Pan American Airlines: Flight Attendant Advisory Board: Minutes, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pan American Airlines: Form Letters, 1977-1986 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Pan American Airlines: General, 1978-1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Pan American Airlines: General, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Pan American Airlines: Holding Company, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Pan American Airlines: Phone Checks, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Pan American Airlines: In-Flight Sales, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Pan American Airlines: Monthly Briefing Notes, 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Pan American Airlines: National Merger, 1978-1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Pan American Airlines: Passport to Prizes ("Greenstamp" Program), 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Pan American Airlines: "Progress" Bulletin, 1981-1985 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Pan American Airlines: "Quipper" Bulletin, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Pan American Airlines: "Taking Care" Bulletin, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Pan American Airlines: Travel Policy, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Pay Case (Hesse), 1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Penalty Clause, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Plight of the Collective Bargaining System (State Assembly of New York report), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Safety/Security Training, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Safety/Security Training, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Scheduling Policy, 1983, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Scheduling Case (Hesse), 1980 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Scheduling Policy, 1977-1988 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Strike Pay, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Superior Customer Service, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Suspension for "Lounge Loitering", 1985 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Teamsters: "Strike", 1983, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Telephone Committee, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Travelers' Insurance Company, 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - TWU Raid, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Underground Airline, 1985-1988 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Understaffing, 1979-1983 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Unemployment Case, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Vacation, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Vacation, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Vacation Days Lost, 1978-1982 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Winter of Discontent, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Weight Policy, 1981-1984 (Box 3, Folder 44)